TheChaosLegion
I want to shine on you, and always like that dazzling sun.
I will defend you from all the darkness.
This is the truth from my heart.
If only our hearts could connect, I could get you to believe me.
Even if you can't see it now, don't lose it.
Your kindness won't be in vain.
You'll be carried aloft by the wind to somewhere that isn't here.
You'll cross the sea and cross time, and I know you'll blossom one day.
Whatever the day, I'll be there for you.
I hope I can watch over you like the sun for all time.
This is the truth from my heart.
～♪
Moribito Guardian of the Spirit
（帝(みかど)）いよいよ そなたも
年立ちの月で晴れて成人となり―
With the first month of the new year,
you will finally come of age...
宮中(きゅうちゅう)での帯刀を許されることとなる
...and you will be permitted to wear
a sword within the imperial court.
You are aware of this, I take it?
（帝）そのことは知っておるな？
（サグム）はい
I am.
As your father, I intend to
bestow a sword upon you today.
今日は 父として そなたに
一振りの刀を授けようと思うてな
サグムよ
Sagum...
May you wear it in good health.
これからも健やかでな
Thank you, Father.
（サグム）
ありがとうございます 父上
Episode 15
Untimely Death
（シュガ）“100年に一度の
大いなる乾ノ相(かわきのそう)は―”
"The sign of the great drought..."
"...which appears once
every hundred years..."
"...is a natural consequence of the
aged Nyunga Ro Im approaching death."
“老いたニュンガ･ロ･イムが―”
“死にいくときに起こる
必然の相なり”
必然だと？
Natural consequence?
If that is true, then perhaps we
cannot determine if the prince is alive...
となると 乾ノ相だけから―
皇子の生死を判断することは
できないのかもしれんな
...using only the sign of
the great drought as a guide.
Teacher, you're not a young woman
any more. You shouldn't push yourself.
（タンダ）
師匠 もう いい年なんですから―
むちゃしないでくださいよ
None of your cheek, youngster.
（トロガイ）黙れ 小わっぱ
There are times when you can't get
to the truth unless you push yourself.
むちゃをせねば
真理に たどり着けんこともある
ヤマビメが食いたい
I have a craving for yamabime.
Boy. Fetch me some yamabime
from the mountains out back.
（トロガイ）小僧
裏山からヤマビメを採ってこい
（チャグム）ヤマビメ？
Yamabime?
What, you don't even
know what yamabime are?
何じゃ ヤマビメも知らんのか
They're a purple fruit with
a clean split down the middle.
紫色のパックリ割れた果物じゃ
Go onto any mountain and you'll
find them hanging from trees all over!
山に入れば
いくらでも ぶら下がっとるわ
Hurry up and fetch me some!
さっさと採ってこんかい！
（チャグム）あっ…
Go on by yourself.
１人で行っといで
山に入れば すぐに見つかるよ
You'll find some right away
once you reach the mountains.
All right.
分かった
あの小僧 死ぬよ
That boy is going to die.
What are you talking about?
何を言いだすんです？
I thought you said that the egg
wouldn't harm its guardian.
確か 卵は
守り人を傷つけることはないと…
The egg won't.
卵はな
There's something that you
haven't told us yet, isn't there?
まだ 私たちに話していない何かが
あるんですね
I couldn't say anything
with the boy sitting there.
今まで あの小僧がいたんでな
どうやらナユグから―
Apparently, something called "Rarunga"
is going to come here from Nayug.
ラルンガなるものが
やって来るらしい
And what's that?
（タンダ）何です？ そいつは
（トロガイ）あいにく
詳しいことは聞けなかったが―
Unfortunately, I wasn't able
to learn anything specific...
ヨナ･ロ･ガイたちは
卵食いと言っておった
...but the Yona Ro Gai
called it an egg-eater.
だが そもそも
生き物なのかすらも分からん
I don't even know if
it's a living creature.
Is there a chance that it
will attack him right now?
今すぐ襲ってくる可能性は？
あっ…
卵が かえるまで チャグムを―
Can't we just hide Chagum
somewhere until the egg hatches?
どこかに かくまうってのは
ダメなんですか？
ダメだね 卵は―
That won't do any good.
Apparently, it can't hatch
unless it's taken to...
宴(うたげ)の地なる場所に行かねば
かえることができないようだ
...something called
the Land of Feasting.
（タンダ）宴の地？
Land of Feasting?
Where is that?
それは どこなんです？
I don't know that, either.
それも分からん
This must be it...
これか
On the other hand,
I did learn when the egg will hatch.
（トロガイ）だが
いつ 卵が かえるのかは聞けたよ
サグの春の等しき日だそうだ
They say it'll be on
Sagu's spring day of equality.
春の等しき日？
Spring day of equality?
The vernal equinox, most likely.
（トロガイ）春分じゃろ
昼と夜の長さが同じになる日さ
That's the day when day
and night are the same length.
その日になったら 全ては
小僧本人が教えてくれるそうじゃ
They said that on that day, the boy
himself will explain everything to us.
それまでは
小僧も大丈夫ってことらしい
Until then, the boy will be safe.
卵食いが来るのも
そのころじゃろう
The egg-eater probably won't
turn up until sometime around then.
ここで とやかく言っていても
始まりませんね
Sitting around here talking
about it isn't going to help matters.
まずは そのラルンガってのが
何者なのかを―
Let's start by finding out
who or what this Rarunga is.
調べることから始めましょう
（トロガイ）
だが もう一度 結び目まで
行ってくるわけにもいかんしな
Yes, but I can't go back to the Knot.
どこかに 手がかりとなるものが
残っていればいいんだがね
Let's just hope that there's still
something for us to go on out there...
なかなかの大物じゃないか
Well, well!
You found some big ones.
They're awfully light
for something so big.
大きさのわりに軽いんだな
おお！ まるまると熟れておるわ
These are plump and ripe!
わしが
うら若き乙女だったころも―
Back when I was a young girl...
...the storytelling hag of the village
often sent me out to pick these for her.
村の語り部の ばばあに
よく取りに行かされたもんじゃ
そうだ！ 師匠 それですよ
（トロガイ）うん？
Mistress, that's it!
A Yakoo storyteller
might know something.
ヤクーの語り部なら あるいは…
All the Yakoo around here have pretty
much assimilated into Yogoan culture.
ここいらのヤクーは もはや
ヨゴ人と同化しちまってるからね
正確な伝承が伝わっているかは
怪しいよ
I doubt that the oral histories they tell
have been handed down accurately.
What about Toumi village?
トウミ村なら どうでしょう？
俺の じいさんが
移り住んだ あの村なら―
The old oral histories
might have survived...
...out in the village
my grandfather moved to.
伝承が残っているかもしれませんよ
確かに あの くそ田舎なら―
True, it might be worth going
out to that godforsaken village.
行ってみる価値は
あるかもしれんな
手を こまねいているよりは
マシです
It's better than sitting
around doing nothing.
Are we going somewhere?
どこかに行くのか？
うん？
ああ… 調べ物をするための旅だ
Yes, on a journey to
get some information.
旅か それは楽しみだ
A journey? That sounds like
something to look forward to.
I guess you'll go check it out, then.
（トロガイ）行ってみるかね
We'll stop by home first to
make the necessary preparations.
なら 一度 うちに戻って
支度をしてきます
I'll go with you, then.
俺も一緒に行こう
I want to pick up
some medicinal herbs.
薬草も調達しときたいから
"And then, mammatus clouds appeared
to allow the mother water spirit..."
（シュガ）“母なる水の精霊が―”
“我が子たる卵に
最後の恵みを与えるための―”
“乳房雲が現れる”
"...to bestow her final blessing
upon the egg, her child."
"And then, mammatus clouds appeared
to allow the mother water spirit..."
“母なる水の精霊が―”
“我が子たる卵に
最期の恵みを与えるための―”
"...to bestow her final blessing
upon the egg, her child"?
“乳房雲が現れる”
"Exactly as described in Yakooan oral
tradition, on the last day of summer..."
“ヤクーの伝承と同様
夏の終わりを迎えたる日―”
"...clouds shaped like breasts
appeared directly above the village..."
“精霊の守り人の
居ずまう村の中天に―”
“空を覆い尽くさんばかりの
乳のごとき雲が現れ―”
"...where the guardian of the
spirit lived, blotting out the sky."
"Almost as if the earth
was swallowing them..."
“大地が
雲を吸い尽くすかのごとく―”
“地上の一点に
雲という雲が吸い寄せられ―”
"...every cloud in the sky was drawn
to a single point on the ground..."
"...after which a localized
downpour began to fall."
“局地的な大雨が降り注いだ”
これだ！
This is it! If I can
observe these clouds...
この雲が観測できれば―
チャグム皇子が
生きておられるという証しになる
...it will be the proof I need
that Prince Chagum is alive!
What day is today?
今日は何日だ？
（無人の体(てい)１）
シュガ様 大丈夫でございますか？
Master Shuga?
Is everything all right?
（シュガ）
鍵は 今も聖導師(せいどうし)様の所か？
The master star reader
still has the key?
はい
Yes.
（シュガ）そうか
I see...
何か大事なことが
おありなのですね？
It sounds as if you have
uncovered something important.
I must get out of here
at once to verify something.
今すぐ ここを出て
確かめたいことがあるのだ
分かりました
なんとかしてみましょう
Very well, sir.
We will try to find a way...
（無人の体２）急げ！
Hurry!
Our apologies, sir!
（無人の体２）申し訳ございません
お… おい！
Hey!
すまん
I am sorry...
You have our deepest
apologies, Master.
（無人の体１）
誠に申し訳ございません
（星読み１）
聖導師様に何ということを…
How dare you treat the master
star reader with such disrespect!
Has the heat gone to your head?
Such a lack of discipline!
（星読み２）暑さで ふらついたか？
たるんでおるぞ
That's enough.
（聖導師）もうよい
（無人の体２）早く持ち場へ
Hurry back to your station.
Moribito Guardian of the Spirit
何故 部屋に入った？
Why have you entered
these chambers?
I have no idea what you
are referring to, Master.
何のことでしょうか？
（聖導師）分かっておろうな？
この部屋に無断で入ったことの意味
I take it that you realize the consequences
of entering here without permission.
残念だ
A pity. In your ten years of service...
ここに来て10年 一度として
粗相をしたことがなかった―
...you have never once committed an
offense. I never expected to lose you.
そなたを失うことになろうとは
ついてまいれ
Come with me.
Become empty vessels.
これより無人の体にて！
I am sorry. This is all my fault.
すまない 私のせいで
We wish for nothing more than
Prince Chagum's safe return.
チャグム皇子の ご帰還は
我らの悲願です
あの者も 後悔は ありますまい
I am sure that my
comrade has no regrets.
許せ
Forgive me.
（ガカイ）殿下
Your Highness.
帝より賜れた刀は―
The sword the mikado gave you is...
殿下のお好みとは
少し違うのではありませぬか？
...a bit different than
the style you prefer, isn't it?
The success of a gift is determined by
the attention given to it by the recipient.
贈り物とは 受け取る側の
気配りによって成就するもの
What is important is the sentiment
of the giver and recipient.
大切なのは 双方の気持ちなのだ
I see...
“夏の終わりを迎えたる日”
それが今日 この日なら…
The day that signals summer's end...
If that is today, this very day, then...
Nothing...
ない
The prince is alive!
皇子は生きていらした！
Not only is he alive,
he is right under our noses!
それも 我らの目と鼻の先
光扇京(こうせんきょう)に…
Right here in Kosenkyo!
What a downpour...
すごい夕立だな
It has been a long time since
you were here last, Shuga.
（サグム）そなたが
ここに来るのは 久しぶりじゃな
シュガよ
How did you know it was me?
なぜ 私と お気づきに？
忙しいときほど
感覚は研ぎ澄まされるものだ
One's senses are always heightened
when one is pressed for time.
How are you feeling,
Your Highness?
お体の具合は いかがですか？
It must be because I've been
so focused. I am feeling well.
気を張っているからだろう
調子はよい
Does something trouble you, then?
では 何か心配事でも？
少し… 心が
くたびれているのかもしれん
Perhaps my spirit is
somewhat exhausted.
Your Highness...
殿下…
Playing the role of Crown Prince
Sagum has taken its toll.
皇太子サグムを演じるのは
かなり こたえる
With some effort,
I have managed to endure...
今までは なんとか
努力で しのいできたが―
それも目いっぱいじゃ
...but it now takes every
ounce of my strength.
Your Highness, perhaps you might
delegate some of your duties to others...
殿下 これからは
役を他の者に任せ―
肩の荷を 少し
降ろされては いかがでしょう？
...and lessen the
burden placed on you.
If there were a few people
who were truly able to support me...
余を真に扶翼することのできる者が
あと いくらか おれば―
...that might be possible.
それも可能だろうがな
それにも まして 余には
決定的に欠けているものがある
To make matters worse,
I lack a certain crucial quality.
人の心を
捉えて離さぬ天神の恩ちょう
The divine grace to captivate
people's hearts and not let go.
位で人は動かせても
その心まで動かすことは難しいのう
I might use my rank to
sway people to action...
...but it is rather difficult
to sway their hearts as well.
It was Chagum who had this quality.
それをチャグムは持っておった
自然と人を魅する力をな
He had the innate
ability to charm others.
殿下 チャグム皇子は…
（サグム）そうじゃな
Your Highness,
Prince Chagum is...
Yes, you are right.
チャグムは
もう この世には おらぬ
Chagum is no longer with us.
But it is because he is gone that I am
able to keep going without breaking.
だが チャグムが おらぬからこそ
世は 今も折れずに頑張れるのじゃ
I will do his share, as well.
チャグムの分までな
すまんな
つまらない話を聞かせてしまった
I am sorry. I did not mean
to bore you with trivialities.
Not at all, Highness.
めっそうもございません
私と語らうことで
気分が晴れるのなら―
If speaking with me lifts your spirits,
I shall come whenever you wish.
いつでも参ります
そうか 少し心が晴れた
You will? I do feel
somewhat better now.
Shuga, I hope you will
continue to be a good friend to me.
シュガよ
今後とも余のよき友であってくれ
もちろんです
Of course, Your Highness.
して そなたの用件は何じゃ？
Now then, what is it that
you wished to discuss?
恐れながら 私の思慮が
足らなかったようでございます
My apologies, Your Highness.
I should have exercised better judgement.
いま一度 出直してまいります
I will call upon you another time.
I see.
そうか
３日ばかり 私に
馬を貸してもらえないだろうか？
Could you lend the use of
a horse for three days or so?
Yes, but, well...
しかし 星読み博士が
馬を借りに来たのは―
This is the first time a star reader
has ever borrowed a horse...
初めてのことでして
安心しろ
これでも 元は漁師の出だ
You needn't worry.
I come from a family of fishermen.
I've ridden my share of horses.
馬くらい乗ったことはある
Chagum, that's quite
a tan you have there.
チャグム あんた 日に焼けたね
It is?
そうか？
確かに以前より黒くなったかもな
You know, I think his skin's
darker than it used to be.
You look a little more
muscular now too.
いくらか
たくましくなったんじゃないのか？
そうだね
I think you're right.
Come to think of it, I haven't had
any strange dreams lately, either.
そういえば
最近は 変な夢も見なくなったし
すごく体が軽い気がする
It feels like a huge weight has
been lifted from my shoulders.
これからは 自由に
生きていくんだって思うと―
When I think about how
I'm free to live my life...
...as I see fit from
now on, I get excited.
なんだかワクワクした気分になるよ
Is there something
that you want to do?
チャグムは
何か やりたいことがあるのか？
人のためになって 知りたいことを
追いかけられる仕事がいいな
I'd like to do something
to help other people...
...and also learn about
things that interest me.
You have the
temperament of a scholar...
チャグムは学者肌だから―
在野の学者になって 子供に
ものを教えるのも悪くないかもな
...so maybe you should become a
field scholar and teach the local children.
それじゃ チャグムが
読み書きできる文机でも買おうかね
In that case, maybe I'll buy him a writing
desk so that he can read and write.
What we learned...
Are you going to tell Chagum?
あのこと チャグムに言うのか？
Eventually, I'll probably have
no choice but to tell him.
いずれ言わざるをえないだろうね
But at the moment,
we don't know anything for sure.
でも 今は 確実なことが
何も分かっていないんだ
Oh, right. Take this.
（タンダ）そうだ これ
トウミ村までの地図だ
It's a map to Toumi village.
（シュガ）チャグム皇子が
生きているという証しを持ち帰り―
If I uncover proof that
Prince Chagum is still alive...
聖導師様に ご報告すれば…
...and report my findings
to the master star reader...
...everything will work out!
全て うまくいく！
サグム殿下
Prince Sagum.
This correspondence
has just arrived.
こちらの書簡が届いております
（サグム）
ガカイよ 余は少し疲れた
Gakai, I find myself
a bit exhausted...
Your Highness?
殿下…
You have taught me
a great many things.
そなたは 余に
さまざまなことを教えてくれたな
I am grateful to you.
感謝しておるぞ
もったいない お言葉でございます
You are too kind, Your Highness.
これからは
星読みとしてシュガと協調し―
From now on, I want you to
cooperate with Shuga as a star reader...
...and make the palace
a better place.
この宮を よりよきものにしてくれ
I will.
はい
（サグム）ガカイ
（ガカイ）はっ！
Gakai.
Your Highness?
Will you release
that bird into the sky?
（サグム）あの鳥を
空に放してやってはくれぬか？
（ガカイ）よろしいのですか？
Are you sure, Your Highness?
ああ 余も
そうそう面倒を見ておれんのでな
Yes. I can no longer give it
the attention it deserves.
Indeed. Considering all your duties
as crown prince, perhaps it is time.
確かに 皇太子の職務を考えますと
頃合いかもしれませんな
Go on, fly away!
それ 飛んでいけ
殿下が 行けと おっしゃる
His Highness commands you to fly.
それ 行けというのじゃ
それ！ それ！
Go on! Fly, I say!
Go on... Shoo!
おお うまく飛ぶものですな
It is flying strongly, Your Highness.
Surely the result of the
tender care you lavished upon it.
これも 殿下の手厚い施しの
たまものでしょうな
Farewell...
さらばじゃ
Forgive me, Chagum...
許せ チャグム
As I sat huddled and alone, holding back the tears on those nights...
When it felt like I was about to succumb to my doubts...
...there you were, at my side before I knew it.
It was none other than you who was there for me.
I keep wishing, "I want to be strong." I stumble and hurt myself again.
But because I have you to believe in, I can get back to my feet.
I simply want to tell my dear one, "Thank you."
At the top of my lungs, again and again.
I call out to my precious loved one.
Is my voice reaching you?
In this world that always changes, human warmth never does.
I'm certain I sensed the presence of the one that I hold dear.
～♪
Next Time
Shuga, who has been given full command
over the search for Chagum...
...once again sets the Hunters
loose upon Ogi no Shimo.
Next time,
"With All One's Heart."
Episode 16
With All One's Heart
The unforgettable summer
is about to come to an end.